now sometimes when you do prolonged fasting and
you break the fast by eating you may experience
certain digestive problems so i want to address
that you could experience diarrhea loose stools
gas abdominal pain bloating or nausea now the
reason for all this is because your digestive
system has kind of gone to sleep and it hasn't
woke up yet and i'm talking about the fluids it
could be hydrochloric acid from the stomach it
could be enzymes from the pancreas it could be
bile or it could even be your good bacteria or
flora in certain parts of your digestive tract
you definitely don't want to eat a huge meal and
overload the system so you want to start small
so if you're going for let's say i don't know
48 72 hours or longer the best thing to do
would be to start with some cooked vegetables
with some broth okay wait two hours and then
consume some protein that's easier to digest
and that could be some fish chicken or even
an egg but make sure it's like three ounces not a
lot you can also do like a little bit of avocado
okay so because you just want to ease into this so
you don't overload the system it wouldn't hurt to
also take some apple cider vinegar or obtain
hydrochloride to build up your stomach acid
because the symptoms of low stomach acid
would be gas abdominal bloating and undigested
food lower in the digestive tract you can
also take some purified bile salts to help you
break down certain fats as well and the symptoms
of low bile salts would be like you're nauseated
or you have bloating okay or you might need
some enzymes and that could be also bloating or
pain more on the left side of your lower
rib cage instead of the right the right
would be gall bladder the left would be
more the pancreas you're just not able to
kick in the pancreas to release these enzymes so
taking enzymes we take the stress off the pancreas
now there's also enzymes in the small intestine
that could be asleep too that need to be woken up
a probiotic wouldn't hurt as well especially
if you have diarrhea or loose stools so
the whole point is to ease into this slowly
so you don't overwhelm the system you probably
want to avoid things like nuts nut butters right
off the bat red meat raw cruciferous vegetables
dairy like cheese because all of these need
certain enzymes purify bile salts more acid
to break these things down and if you're
missing them that can be the real problem
now there's also another condition that's
very rare it's called refeeding syndrome now
this would occur if you went for let's say a
week or two weeks of fasting and you're already
nutritionally deficient in certain electrolytes
like potassium phosphorus magnesium calcium
and then you eat a refined carbohydrate or high
sugar food because what's going to happen you're
going to spike insulin and that insulin is going
to take all these electrolytes from your blood and
push them right deep into the cell that's what
insulin does and so you're going to end up with
all sorts of electrolyte deficiencies in
your blood which could make you feel weak
confused and can create a big strain on your
heart about three hours later now you can avoid
this by not having a high carb meal you can
also avoid this by taking certain electrolytes
and nutrients throughout your fast okay because it
all depends on how much reserve you have because
nowadays there's not a lot of people that have a
huge nutrient reserve in their body and if they're
new to fasting and they fast for a long period
of time and then they don't have the necessary
nutrients and they do a high carb diet big mistake
so anyway i wanted to create this video to give
you a little more background on why you may
have digestive problems when you break the fast
and i'm not talking about breaking the fast
doing intermittent fasting i'm talking about
more of a prolonged fast like 72 hours or or
longer all right thanks for watching and i
will see you in the next video hey before you
go if you're benefiting from any of my content
i would love to hear about your success
story please share it in the link down below